Guide to the Montana Legislature (57th: 2001) records 2000-2002
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Montana Legislature (57th: 2001) records
2000-2002
Montana Historical Society Archives
LR 57
Montana. Legislature.
32 linear feet of shelf space
Collection contains records (2000-2002) of the 57th Montana Legislature including minutes of joint, conference, and free conference committees; House of Representatives and Senate standing and select committees; bills and resolutions; journal and status reports; and miscellany of the regular session, the August 2002 special session, and the September 2002 special session. The researcher should note that the audio cassette hearings are only available for Joint committees, Conference and Free Conference committees, House Federal Relations, Energy, and Telecommunications committee, Senate Energy and Telecommunications committee, and House Judiciary committee. [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: oversize box, volumes, map case, and multimedia collection.] To see a list of audio recordings available at MHS for 2001 Click Here.
The Montana State Legislature is made up of two chambers, the Senate and the House of Representatives. The Constitution of Montana limits the size of the Senate to no fewer than 40 and no more than 50 members and the size of the House of Representatives to no fewer than 80 and no more than 100 members. Each house is responsible for choosing its officers, creating committees and establishing its own rules. The Montana Legislature meets for 90 days every odd numbered year, beginning the first Monday in January, or the following Wednesday if the first Monday is New Years Day. The first State Legislature convened on November 23, 1889, fifteen days after Montana became a state. Each following Legislature has been numbered sequentially.
The 57th Montana Legislature met from January 3rd to April 21st, 2001. There were 18 standing committees in the Senate, 16 standing committees in the House, and 6 Joint Appropriations Committees. The leaders of the Senate were Tom Beck (R-President), Walter McNutt (R-President Pro Tempore), Fred Thomas (R-Majority Leader), and Steve Doherty (D-Minority Leader). The leaders of the House were Dan McGee (R-Speaker), Doug Mood (R-Speaker Pro Tempore), Paul Sliter (R-Majority Leader), and Kim Gillan (D-Minority Leader).
Sources:Montana State Legislature Session Information ;The Constitution of the State of Montana as adopted by the Constitutional Convention March 22, 1972, and as ratified by the people, June 6, 1972, referendum no. 68, "A GUIDE TO THE MONTANA LEGISLATURE," The Montana Legislature,; “Montana Legislative Leadership 1889 – Present”.
Collection includes minutes of Joint, conference, and free conference committees; House of Representatives and Senate standing committees; select committees on Local Government Funding; bills and resolutions; and journal and status reports of the regular session, the August 2002 special session, and the September 2002 special session. The collection also contains miscellany material including bill subject index and a sponsor list. The researcher should note that the audio cassette hearings are only available for Joint committees, Conference and Free Conference committees, House Federal Relations, Energy, and Telecommunications committee, Senate Energy and Telecommunications committee, and House Judiciary committee.
The collection is organized into the three subgroups, Regular Session, Special Session, and Second Special Session.
The subgroup Regular Session is organized into these four series, House and Senate Joint Committees, House of Representatives, Senate, and Miscellany. The series House and Senate Joint Committees is organized into these four subseries, Joint Subcommittee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), Joint Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), Conference Committee Minutes (arranged numerically by House and then Senate bill number) and Free Conference Committee Minutes (arranged numerically by House and then Senate bill number). The series House of Representatives is organized into these seven subseries, House Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), House Select Committees Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), House Bills (arranged numerically by bill number), House Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), House Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), House Bill Status Reports (arranged chronologically), and House Journals (arranged chronologically). The series Senate is organized into these six subseries, Senate Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), Senate Bills (arranged numerically by bill number), Senate Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), Senate Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), Senate Bill Status Reports (arranged chronologically), and Senate Journals (arranged chronologically).
The subgroup Special Session is organized into these three series, House and Senate Joint Committees, House of Representatives, and Senate. The series House and Senate Joint Committees is organized into this one subseries, Free Conference Committee Minutes (arranged numerically by House and then Senate bill number). The series House of Representatives is organized into these five subseries, House Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), House Bills (arranged numerically by bill number), House Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), House Bill Status Reports (arranged chronologically), and House Journals (arranged chronologically). The series Senate is organized into these five subseries Senate Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), Senate Bills (arranged numerically by bill number), Senate Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), Senate Bill Status Reports (arranged chronologically), and Senate Journals (arranged chronologically).
The subgroup Second Special Session is organized into these two series, House of Representatives and Senate. The series House of Representatives is organized into these three subseries, House Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), House Bills (arranged numerically by bill number), and House Journals (arranged chronologically). The series Senate is organized into these two subseries Senate Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically) and Senate Journals (arranged chronologically).
Committee hearings available on audio cassette at MHS. Committee hearings are also available on the Montana Legislature website.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
OVERSIZE MATERIAL: oversize box, volumes, map case, and multimedia collection.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Montana. Legislature
Montana--Politics and government
Bills, Legislative--Montana; Legislative bodies--Committees--Montana
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Regular Session
  - House and Senate Joint Committees
    - Joint Subcommittee Minutes
      - Appropriations: Corrections and Public Safety [exhibits from January 12 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see volume 1], 2001 January 5 - February 13 (Box-folder 1 / 1-21)
      - Appropriations: Education [exhibits from January 9, January 16 and January 18 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see volume 2 and oversize box, folder 1], 2001 January 8-25 (Box-folder 1 / 22-34)
      - Appropriations: Education, 2001 January 26 - February 9 (Box-folder 2 / 1-11)
      - Appropriations: General Government and Transportation [exhibits from January 25 and February 1 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 1], 2001 January 5 - February 9 (Box-folder 2 / 12-36)
      - Appropriations: General Government and Transportation, 2001 February 9-19 (Box-folder 3 / 1-7)
      - Appropriations: Health and Human Services [exhibits from January 25 include MULTIMEDIA: see MM 33], 2001 January 5-29 (Box-folder 3 / 8-24)
      - Appropriations: Health and Human Services [exhibits from February 8 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 1], 2001 January 30 - February 19 (Box-folder 4 / 1-16)
      - Appropriations: Information Technology, 2001 January 10 - 31 (Box-folder 4 / 17-21)
      - Appropriations: Long Range Planning, 2001 January 5-8 (Box-folder 4 / 22-23)
      - Appropriations: Long Range Planning [exhibits from January 18, January 25, January 26, January 29, January 30, January 31 and February 6 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 1; exhibits from January 16 and January 22 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see map case], 2001 January 9 - March 21 (Box-folder 5 / 1-30)
      - Appropriations: Natural Resources and Commerce [exhibits from January 5 and January 26 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 1 and map case], 2001 January 5 - March 14 (Box-folder 6 / 1-28)
    - Joint Committee Minutes
      - Rules, 2000 December 8 (Box-folder 6 / 29)
    - Conference Committees Minutes
      - HJ 32 (re requesting legislative performance audit on child protective services), 2001 April 11 (Box-folder 6 / 30)
      - HB 118 (re revising clean air act), 2001 April 10 (Box-folder 6 / 31)
      - HB 119 (re clarifying hearings officer use by board of pardons and parole), 2001 April 17 (Box-folder 6 / 32)
      - HB 124 (re revising local government funding), 2001 April 12 (Box-folder 6 / 33)
      - HB 172 (re county hospital employee exemption from mandated leave), 2001 April 5 (Box-folder 6 / 34)
      - HB 208 (re revising contempt of court laws), 2001 April 17 (Box-folder 6 / 35)
      - HB 216 (re increasing fines for minor purchasing alcohol or tobacco), 2001 April 10 (Box-folder 6 / 36)
      - HB 226 (re allocating portion of federal mineral royalty funds to counties), 2001 April 17 (Box-folder 6 / 37)
      - HB 266 (re revising governmental accountability act), 2001 April 10 (Box-folder 6 / 38)
      - HB 290 (re including deception, coercion, surprise in definition of without consent for rape), 2001 April 17 (Box-folder 6 / 39)
      - HB 324 (re licensure for drop-in day care), 2001 April 12 (Box-folder 6 / 40)
      - HB 359 (re expanding DNA database to all felonies), 2001 April 17 (Box-folder 6 / 41)
      - HB 360 (re revising sexual offense laws), 2001 April 17 (Box-folder 6 / 42)
      - HB 559 (re revising notice periods for termination of landlord-tenant rental agreements), 2001 April 10-12 (Box-folder 6 / 43-44)
      - HB 572 (re adjusting and redistributing money derived from natural gas from coal beds), 2001 April 11 (Box-folder 6 / 45)
      - HB 603 (re revising agency notice of appeals to attorney general), 2001 April 12 (Box-folder 6 / 46)
      - HB 612 (re generally revising election laws), 2001 April 17 (Box-folder 6 / 47)
      - HB 625 (re interim study of school funding), 2001 April 18 (Box-folder 6 / 48)
      - HB 644 (re reducing state fuel tax on ethanol and biodiesel - replacement for tax revenue), 2001 April 17 (Box-folder 6 / 49)
      - SB 4 (re clarifying discharge from employment during probationary period), 2001 March 23 - April 19 (Box-folder 6 / 50-51)
      - SB 28 (re revising process for modification of child support orders), 2001 April 6 (Box-folder 6 / 52)
      - SB 48 (re clarifying out-of-state direct shipment of alcoholic beverages to Montanans), 2001 April 6 (Box-folder 6 / 53)
      - SB 57 (re extending universal system benefits charge), 2001 April 12 (Box-folder 6 / 54)
      - SB 135 (re revising laws governing mental health managed care ombudsman), 2001 April 9 (Box-folder 6 / 55)
      - SB 242 (re prohibiting extraterritorial building codes), 2001 April 9-10 (Box-folder 6 / 56)
      - SB 283 (re revising citizen review board laws), 2001 April 9 (Box-folder 6 / 57)
      - SB 320 (re state purchase of renewable fuel vehicles), 2001 April 9 (Box-folder 6 / 58)
      - SB 322 (re natural resources worker education and retraining), 2001 April 18 (Box-folder 6 / 59)
      - SB 348 (re clarifying sounding of locomotive horn at public crossings), 2001 April 10 (Box-folder 6 / 60)
      - SB 390 (re revising school finance laws - flexibility program), 2001 April 9 (Box-folder 6 / 61)
      - SB 423 (re petition to create single member school trustee districts), 2001 April 10 (Box-folder 6 / 62)
      - SB 427 (re limited county general obligation bonds for roads and highways), 2001 April 7 (Box-folder 6 / 63)
      - SB 429 (re revising local government referendum / election laws), 2001 April 11 (Box-folder 6 / 64)
      - SB 432 (re clarifying funding for aerospace transportation and technology infrastructure), 2001 April 10-12 (Box-folder 6 / 65-66)
      - SB 437 (re supplemental game damage licenses), 2001 April 9 (Box-folder 6 / 67)
      - SB 441 (re study funding for comprehensive health plan), 2001 April 10 (Box-folder 6 / 68)
      - SB 457 (re authorizing use of impact aid for school bonding), 2001 April 17 (Box-folder 6 / 69)
      - SB 514 (re revising reporting of gain or loss from sale of real property), 2001 April 13 (Box-folder 6 / 70)
    - Free Conference Committees Minutes
      - Energy policy (HB 474, HB 632, HB 645, SB 19, SB 21, SB 398), 2001 April 16- 19 (Box-folder 7 / 1-4)
      - Energy tax (HB 600, HB 646; SB 505, SB 506, SB 508, SB 512), 2001 April 16- 19 (Box-folder 7 / 5-8)
      - HB 2 (re general appropriations), 2001 April 10- 20 (Box-folder 7 / 9-15)
      - HB 5 (re appropriating money for capital projects), 2001 April 18- 19 (Box-folder 7 / 16-17)
      - HB 41 (re revising laws governing dedicated revenue and statutory appropriations), 2001 April 18 (Box-folder 7 / 18)
      - HB 124 (re revising local government funding) [exhibits from April 18, 5pm, include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 4], 2001 April 17- 18 (Box-folder 7 / 19-23)
      - HB 142 (re authorizing rules restricting nonresident mountain lion licenses), 2001 April 6- 20 (Box-folder 7 / 24-25)
      - HB 146 and SB 386 (re revising youth court act and making intervention in delinquency pilot program permanent), 2001 April 18 (Box-folder 7 / 26)
      - HB 293 (re Secretary of State to break tie votes in elections), 2001 April 4 (Box-folder 7 / 27)
      - HB 459 (re generally revising MEPA), 2001 April 11 (Box-folder 7 / 28)
      - HB 473 (re revising MEPA), 2001 April 6-11 (Box-folder 7 / 29-30)
      - HB 474 (re revising energy laws pertaining to large customers), 2001 April 20 (Box-folder 7 / 31)
      - HB 573 (re allowing oil and gas board to permit certain coal bed methane gas wells), 2001 April 17- 20 (Box-folder 7 / 32-34)
      - HB 605 (re revising laws governing local and state air quality regulation), 2001 April 12 (Box-folder 7 / 35)
      - HB 637 (re office of restorative justice), 2001 April 18 (Box-folder 7 / 36)
      - SB 151 (re prohibiting government sale of fitness services), 2001 April 10 (Box-folder 7 / 37)
      - SB 176 (re revising district court funding - state assumption), 2001 April 19 (Box-folder 7 / 38)
      - SB 185 (re revising campaign finance and reporting law), 2001 April 9 (Box-folder 7 / 39)
      - SB 196 (re requiring country of origin placarding on meat and produce), 2001 April 6 (Box-folder 7 / 40)
      - SB 242 (re prohibiting extraterritorial building codes), 2001 April 18 (Box-folder 7 / 41)
      - SB 327 (re restricting government competition with private internet service providers), 2001 April 11 (Box-folder 7 / 42)
      - SB 390 (re revising school finance laws - flexibility program), 2001 April 10 (Box-folder 7 / 43)
      - SB 432 (re clarifying funding for aerospace transportation and technology infrastructure), 2001 April 17- 19 (Box-folder 7 / 44-46)
      - SB 437 (re supplemental game damage licenses), 2001 April 11- 20 (Box-folder 7 / 47-48)
  - House of Representatives
    - House Standing Committee Minutes
      - Agriculture [exhibits from January 16, January 18, and February 6 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see map case], 2001 January 9 - March 27 (Box-folder 7 / 49-68)
      - Appropriations [for January 4 meeting, see Senate Finance], 2001 January 5 - March 27 (Box-folder 8 / 1-54)
      - Appropriations, 2001 April 2-5 (Box-folder 9 / 1-7)
      - Business and Labor [exhibits from January 11, February 7, March 14, March 23, and March 27 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 2; exhibits from March 14 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see map case], 2001 January 4- April 11 (Box-folder 9 / 8-62)
      - Education, 2001 January 5 - April 2 (Box-folder 10 / 1-30)
      - Ethics, 2001 January 11 - February 1 (Box-folder 10 / 31-33)
      - Federal Relations, Energy, and Telecommunications, 2001 January 4 - April 10 (Box-folder 10 / 34-58)
      - Fish, Wildlife, and Parks [exhibits from January 23 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 2], 2001 January 9 - April 10 (Box-folder 11 / 1-21)
      - Human Services [exhibits from March 5 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 2], 2001 January 8 - April 18 (Box-folder 11 / 22-49)
      - Human Services subcommittee, 2001 March 13 (Box-folder 11 / 50)
      - Judiciary, 2001 January 4-15 (Box-folder 11 / 51-58)
      - Judiciary, 2001 January 16 - March 22 (Box-folder 12 / 1-41)
      - Judiciary, 2001 March 23-28 (Box-folder 13 / 1-4)
      - Legislative Administration, 2001 January 23 - March 20 (Box-folder 13 / 5-5d)
      - Local Government, 2001 January 9 - March 27 (Box-folder 13 / 6-25)
      - Natural Resources [exhibits from February 5, February 12, and February 19 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 2; exhibits from February 9 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see map case; exhibits from February 2 include MULTIMEDIA: see MM 34], 2001 January 5 - March 19 (Box-folder 13 / 26-52)
      - Natural Resources, 2001 March 21 - April 9 (Box-folder 14 / 1-6)
      - Natural Resources subcommittee on HB 69, 2001 March 13-17 (Box-folder 14 / 7)
      - Rules, 2000 December 8 (Box-folder 14 / 8)
      - State Administration, 2001 January 8 - March 28 (Box-folder 14 / 9-50)
      - Taxation [exhibits from January 23 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 2], 2001 January 9 - February 7 (Box-folder 14 / 51-70)
      - Taxation, 2001 February 8 - April 18 (Box-folder 15 / 1-31)
      - Transportation [exhibits from January 19 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 2; exhibits from January 8 and January 24 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see map case], 2001 January 5 - February 5 (Box-folder 15 / 32-47)
      - Transportation [exhibits from March 19 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see map case], 2001 February 7 - March 26 (Box-folder 16 / 1-16)
    - House Select Committees Minutes
      - Local Government Funding, 2001 February 1- March 6 (Box-folder 16 / 17-23)
    - House Bills
      - Bill nos. 1-91, 2001 (Box-folder 16 / 24-29)
      - Bill nos. 92-311, 2001 (Box-folder 17 / 1-16)
      - Bill nos. 312-636, 2001 (Box-folder 18 / 1-14)
      - Bill nos. 637-650, 2001 (Box-folder 19 / 1-2)
    - House Joint Resolutions
      - Bill nos. 1-44, 2001 (Box-folder 19 / 3-4)
    - House Resolutions
      - Bill nos. 1-2, 2001 (Box-folder 19 / 5)
    - House Bill Status Reports
      - 1st Legislative Day - 90th Legislative Day (includes Introduced Bill Status Report), 2000 December 27 - 2001 April 26 (Box-folder 19 / 6-11)
    - House Journals
      - 1st Legislative Day - 90th Legislative Day, 2001 January 3 - April 21 (Box-folder 19 / 12-18)
  - Senate
    - Senate Standing Committee Minutes
      - Agriculture, Livestock, and Irrigation [exhibits from March 7 and March 21 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 3], 2001 January 5 - March 26 (Box-folder 20 / 1-27)
      - Business and Labor [exhibits from February 16 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 3], 2001 January 9 - March 20 (Box-folder 20 / 27-69)
      - Business and Labor, 2001 March 21 - April 6 (Box-folder 21 / 1-7)
      - Education and Cultural Resources, 2001 January 5 - April 12 (Box-folder 21 / 8-37)
      - Education and Cultural Resources subcommittee, 2001 January 25 - February 2 (Box-folder 21 / 38-40)
      - Energy and Telecommunications [exhibits from February 8 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 3], 2001 January 9 - March 20 (Box-folder 21 / 41-59)
      - Energy and Telecommunications, 2001 March 22 - April 9 (Box-folder 22 / 1-12)
      - Energy and Telecommunications subcommittee, 2001 January 30 (Box-folder 22 / 12a)
      - Finance (includes January 4 joint meeting with House Appropriations), 2001 January 4 - April 16 (Box-folder 22 / 13-45)
      - Fish and Game [exhibits from March 6 contain OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 3], 2001 January 9 - March 6 (Box-folder 22 / 46-58)
      - Fish and Game, 2001 March 8-20 (Box-folder 23 / 1-4)
      - Highways and Transportation [exhibits from February 1 and March 8 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 3; exhibits from April 12 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see map case], 2001 January 9 - April 12 (Box-folder 23 / 5-27)
      - Judiciary [exhibits from February 16 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see map case], 2001 January 4 - February 16 (Box-folder 23 / 28-58)
      - Judiciary [exhibits from March 5 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 3], 2001 February 17 - April 11 (Box-folder 24 / 1-25)
      - Judiciary subcommittee, 2001 February 2-17 (Box-folder 24 / 26-29)
      - Legislative Administration, 2001 January 18 - Mar 27 (Box-folder 24 / 30-33)
      - Local Government [exhibits from January 25, and February 6 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 3], 2001 January 9 - April 3 (Box-folder 24 / 34-55)
      - Natural Resources, 2001 January 5-15 (Box-folder 24 / 56-60)
      - Natural Resources [exhibits from February 14, March 2, and March 9 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 3; exhibits from March 19 include MULTIMEDIA: see MM 35], 2001 January 17 - April 17 (Box-folder 25 / 1-27)
      - Public Health, Welfare, and Safety [exhibits from January 19 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 3], 2001 January 5 - March 2 (Box-folder 25 / 28-49)
      - Public Health, Welfare, and Safety, 2001 March 5-28 (Box-folder 26 / 1-6)
      - Rules, 2000 December 8 - 2001 January 3 (Box-folder 26 / 7-8)
      - State Administration [exhibits from April 5 include OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see oversize box, folder 3], 2001 January 8 - April 16 (Box-folder 26 / 9-63)
      - Taxation, 2001 January 9 - February 15 (Box-folder 26 / 64-84)
      - Taxation, 2001 February 16 - April 3 (Box-folder 27 / 1-31)
      - Taxation subcommittee, 2001 March 26 - April 6 (Box-folder 27 / 31a-34)
    - Senate Bills
      - Bill nos. 1-97, 2001 (Box-folder 27 / 35-40)
      - Bill nos. 98-328, 2001 (Box-folder 28 / 1-14)
      - Bill nos. 329-521, 2001 (Box-folder 29 / 1-11)
    - Senate Joint Resolutions
      - Bill nos. 1-24, 2001 (Box-folder 29 / 12)
    - Senate Resolutions
      - Bill nos. 1-25, 2001 (Box-folder 29 / 13)
    - Senate Bill Status Reports
      - 1st Legislative Day - 51st Legislative Day, 2000 December 27 - 2001 March 6 (Box-folder 29 / 14-15)
      - 51st Legislative Day - 90th Legislative Day (includes Introduced Bill Status Report), 2001 March 7 - April 26 (Box-folder 30 / 1-3)
    - Senate Journals
      - 1st Legislative Day - 70th Legislative Day, 2001 January 3 - March 28 (Box-folder 30 / 4-6)